this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer or /
software this is Nate black for software
engineering radio my guest today is
Jonathan stark Jonathan is a recognized
expert in mobile technology who advises
businesses on their mobile strategy
tactics and training he is the author of
several books on mobile app development
for O'Reilly media including building
iPhone apps with HTML CSS and JavaScript
jonathan is the host of his own podcast
ditching hourly with jonathan stark and
as a regular panelist on the freelancers
show on dev chat TV Jonathan welcome to
software engineering radio hey thanks
for having me Jonathan a lot of our
listeners might be interested in mobile
development but overwhelmed at all the
different technologies that are out
there and maybe even wondering what are
the mobile platforms that are available
in 2017 when we're talking about mobile
apps what are we talking about
yeah that's it's a lot isn't it so I'll
give you a little background when the
iPhone was announced in 2007 I at that
time I was a web developer so low you
know self-employed independent
contractor consultant and I was doing
web development and when the iPhone came
out it just immediately clicked with me
and I was like this that's what I'm
doing from now on that's it that's the
new thing and it was I was sort of I
think lucky in that regard because I
immediately jumped on that as a thing
that was it wasn't that I thought it was
gonna be huge it was just that it was
the it was something that I just
personally wanted so bad you know I was
right in the target market of that
person that was carrying her on a Palm
Pilot and an iPod and all this all these
accoutrements that I just you know I was
like man that's exactly what I want
awesome no no yucky keyboard all screen
that sounds great pinch-to-zoom
my god so I was totally blown away by
that and threw mice but but I was a web
developer and when the the iPod iPhone
was initially announced there was no
there was going to be no App Store
explicitly it was said by Steve Jobs his
mouth that the way that you were going
to develop for this platform was to make
web apps and I was super excited about
that because I was already a web
developer and I don't straight into
figuring out you know exactly how to
make that work so at the very very
beginning it was simple building a
mobile app for iPhone because obviously
that's what we're talking about here
iPhone and Android building a mobile app
for that platform at that time was
building a website that was finger
friendly and formatted to you know be
suitable to that form factor you know a
very small touch screen environment fast
forward ten years you know just it was
like the tenth anniversary just recently
of the iPhone now Android is enormous
it's it's bigger than iPhone you know in
terms of units shipped and the the
landscape has dramatically changed since
then so now I think it's fair to say
that mobile computing is the dominant
computing platform on planet Earth
it's in terms of a variety of things you
know unit shipments are something like
three to four times more than desktop
shipments the usage patterns on mobile
are dramatically higher people spend a
lot more time on their mobiles than they
do on a desktop or laptop computer the
traffic Internet traffic is higher on
mobile email opens are higher on mobile
Mobile mobile mobile all the way down
the chain so in that 10-year period
mobile computing has become the primary
computing platform and the the landscape
has become as big as and bigger in fact
than the desktop landscape ever was so
it's a huge huge complicated question
and for me when I started it was it was
easy to stand out in what was at the
time a relatively small pool
if you wanted to be a world-renowned you
know mobile web developer it wasn't that
hard because there were none you know in
January of 2007 and then in February of
2007 there was at least one and that was
me so you know and there were a few
others you know names that popped mind
but there weren't that many and it was
it was easy to attract the attention of
people who were interested in that other
people who immediately dropped that the
iPhone was gonna be a big thing and
later Android so O'Reilly came around
and I was talking to a senior editor
there wrote a book called you know that
you mentioned building an iPhone apps
with HTML CSS and JavaScript which was
at the time one of a kind who was it was
essentially how to build what is now
called a progressive web app with the
technology that existed at the time to
create a an app like experience in the
web browser and by app like the only
things most of the things we really had
to look at were the internal iOS apps
like the settings application the music
application so scrolling lists that with
drill down and you know toolbars and
that sort of thing so now it was very
straightforward back then now for me the
concept of mobile development is you
know a hundred times more diffuse than
that it's almost like you have to pick a
specific area to specialize in in order
to even have a conversation about what
it is that you do in mobile I'll give
you a couple of examples so of course
you can make a mobile app and by mobile
app when I say that I mean a native
mobile app built with Xcode or Eclipse
or Android studio or whatever that is
published in an app store that is
downloaded through an app store and
installed locally on the device not
something that runs in a web browser
it's it's a full you know a first-class
citizen in the operating system that can
be granted access to things like the
sensors and the radios and
the actuators and the contacts and other
information personal information about
the person who owns the phone so there's
that and that's probably what most
people think about when they think about
mobile development they think oh I want
to make native apps I want an app in the
App Store but there are a lot of other
things that developers can do that I
would still file under mobile
development that are not they're not
that sort of basic concept of building a
mobile app another thing could be
building progressive web apps for you
know a business's web experience that
needs to be for some reason needs to be
sort of higher fidelity than what you
would consider a normal static website
or a normal database driven website like
a wordpress site or something there are
other aspects of the operating system
that your app can reach into so mobile
development also includes things like
widgets in the Today drawer on iOS or
home screen widgets on Android which is
a different kind of runtime a different
kind of development paradigm different
kind of interaction with the user
another kind of mobile development is
developing for sort of the constellation
of of peripherals that surround mobile
now so you could be developing mobile
apps for a phone would be a native app
but really it needs it's meant to
integrate with a security camera or a
native app that that really is just
there to install a watch face on a
SmartWatch Android wear or Apple watch
it's I mean there's a million things -
interactive notifications is another
kind of mobile development you know you
could specialize in developing
interactive notifications so that lets
say a bank can send you a balance a low
balance notice and you can in it shows
up as a notification on whatever
platform and you tap on it and it drills
straight into either could could drill
into a native app for the bank it could
drill into a bot inside of the
what messenger is just a million things
that can happen in something as simple
as an interactive push notification yet
another kind of mobile development is
and I'll stop at this one because there
are more but another kind of mobile
development I just alluded to which is
is integrating inside of applications
that are already installed that really
the top ten applications that are
already installed on everybody's phone
so pretty much everybody's got a Maps
application pretty much everyone's got a
chat application pretty much everyone's
got some sort of one of the one or more
of the big social media applications and
instead of trying to you know create
your own mobile app which almost feels
monolithic to me now and get people to
install it and spend all that money to
acquire users you could just build an
app experience inside of one of these
other apps that's already on somebody's
phone so let's say you work in the
enterprise and you want to build a air
quotes mobile app or a mobile experience
you could just create a slack bot
because all of your users already have
the slack app installed and you don't
have to go through that discovery and
installation process that you don't have
to get over that hurdle with your users
because they already have slack so you
just you just create a bot and in a way
or I still call that mobile development
but it's it's certainly not in the
spirit of your original question which
is what's the landscape of mobile
development so I don't want too much
information
but mobile has become such a universe of
possibilities that it's really become
that complicated that is an excellent
answer and I think it illustrates just
how complex the landscape is you you
mentioned progressive web apps a few
times could you drill into that a little
bit and explain what is a progressive
web app sure quick a quick summary of
that quick answer to that question is
that it's it's a web page that runs in a
browser on the device but it has so many
characteristics of a native application
that it's it's it would be confusing to
call it a web page so
it's called a web app the word
progressive comes in there because the
way that you write these is in an
extremely defensive way so you assume
nothing used you assume that you know
the capabilities of the browser because
a mobile user could run your progressive
web app in Safari or Chrome or Firefox
or opera they could be on Android they
could be on a recent version of Android
an old version of Android a recent
version of iOS the old version of iOS
you don't really know so in a web space
in a browser runtime you have to be
extremely defensive and just assume
nothing and say ok you build you build
the app like an onion from the inside
out which is why it's progressive so
your app starts off by saying you know
I'm not even going to assume that I've
got a network connection I'm not going
to assume that this browser has hardly
any capabilities at all
and I'm you know they're gonna make a
request to a domain you know a URI and
I'm gonna return everything I can to
bootstrap this experience and if it
turns out that the browser environment
is horrible or the the OS is horrible
and it doesn't have the capabilities I
need I'm gonna give them a standard web
page and they'll be able to interact
with my business or service or
experience in a way that they can get
done what they want to get done but if
it turns out that they have just to pick
one out of the air service workers
available in the browser then what I'm
gonna do is install a bunch of offline
code so that the next time they come to
this page first I'm gonna check and say
hey do I have an internet connection if
I don't I've got a bunch of really smart
fallbacks in place locally installed on
the phone in the browser that will allow
them to get what they want to get done
done and later on it'll sync with the
server when they do have a connection so
that you know then there are all sorts
of user interface affordances to make it
feel like a native application you know
understanding touch and multi-touch and
swipe and pinch and you know
multi-finger gestures and those sorts of
things so it's this it's a it's really
an approach to developing a web app that
creates incredibly resilient
piece of code I guess so you end up with
this fast app that can run in any
browser that is is gonna probably
deliver a different experience in every
environment but is going to allow your
users to get on what they want to get
done with whatever tools they currently
have available to them so it's very it's
very slick but it's as complicated as it
sounds which is very complicated it
sounds like there is some disadvantage
in that it's complex to develop that app
but it must have some balancing
advantage what's the advantage why do
people choose to develop progressive web
apps sure okay so there's really two
levels for that question one is why
would I develop a web app at all instead
of a native app and the answer to that
question is that you want to reach the
widest range of users so certain
businesses don't need to reach the
entire world they don't read to reach
the four billion people that have
smartphones or smell the cell phones
anyway they don't need to reach that
large of an audience they only care
about people who have Android because
they sell Android things or they only
care about people who have iPhones
because they think that that's the the
top end of the market and we only care
about rich people or whatever some
businesses don't care about reaching the
broadest possible user base but if you
do care about reaching the broadest
possible user base you probably going to
lean toward a web solution versus a
native solution at first you should
probably have both eventually but at
first when you're deciding how to deploy
your resources over time having a really
nice mobile web experience is a really
good first step so that's a reason why
you might want to go with a web
experience why you would go with a
progressive web experience is that it's
really that it's really more of the same
you know the using a progressive
approach gives you even broader reach
within the the web space so as I
described there are still lots of older
browsers and older devices in
circulation and if you take a what I
would call a standard
non-progressive mobile web app approach
usually what ends up happening is is the
developer creates something really slick
and in you know beautiful and a really
immersive mobile web experience but it
only works on the latest devices in a
couple of browsers like Safari in Chrome
and that's it because they use features
without regard to they basically use
newer features that aren't available in
all their stuff so things break in older
older devices so using a progressive
approach is more complicated but it's
going to you know deliver the best brand
experience for everyone so if you have a
really really diffuse user base trying
to think of something like well one one
I worked on was for the Red Cross and
they needed to have really good offline
support because it was it was this
particular application was meant to be
in available on phones for people who
are going into disaster areas so it was
almost certain that they weren't gonna
have internet even on a cell phone so it
needs to be something where you know at
the airport on their way they could
visit this application it would install
itself locally on their phone so that
when they got to even though it was in a
web browser so when they got to where
they were going they could pull it open
and say like okay I'm on the ground
I see the actual situation and I won't
even go into some of the examples
because it's terrifying but okay I've
got this horrible situation I'm freaking
out everybody's freaking out I don't
have an internet access what do I do and
they can open up this web page and it
sounds like an oxymoron but it's a web
page that works offline an offline web
app and they can you know search it and
find the piece of information that they
need in the moment so it's so it depends
on your use case which whether or not a
progressive web app is work is the right
move for your company depends on who
you're trying to reach what their
expectations are what they're trying to
get done you know it's it's not it's not
like I'm certainly the last person to
say everybody who builds a website
should be building a progressive
so that it could be used on every single
phone you know I'm not like that you
know people have limited resources and
they have to decide what they're going
to do but that's that's why you would
pick something like that could you
contrast progressive web apps with
native mobile apps in particular you
mentioned that progressive web apps are
loaded in the browser how our native
mobile apps distributed okay great
question typically the most common way
that you would distribute a native app
is through a platform app store so in
iOS it's the app store that's on you
know pre-installed on iOS devices and on
Android it would be the Play Store or
possibly if you're on a fire device
you know Amazon fire device from Android
to be Android based newbie the Amazon
store so there are pros and cons to that
you know going through somebody else's
store that are not dissimilar to a
physical bricks and mortar retail
environment so if you sell soap and you
you want to get it to people you've kind
of got two options you can spin up a
Shopify store and sell your soap or you
can deploy your salespeople to try and
get it placed in Walmart and if you get
it in Walmart you are going to have to
play by Walmart's rules in many ways and
they might might tell you how you're
gonna price your soap they might tell
you how much money they're gonna take
from you to sell your soap they might
tell you how much you have to make you
know there so there's a lot of there's a
lot of you know it's it's a let's call
it a partnership I think it's a little
one-sided in most cases but it's the
same way with a platform app store for
the sake of conversation I'll just talk
about the iOS App Store because that's
the one it seems most people care about
so the iOS app store you you would if
you were gonna put a true pure native
iOS app on people's phones the way you
would go to through that process
you design your app you would build it
on a Mac using Xcode and you would sign
it with apples security certificates you
would upload it to their store but you
would register as an apple developer an
iOS developer I should say you pay them
to be an iOS developer you'd do all the
things I just said you upload it through
iTunes Connect it would go through a
review process by people at Apple to
make sure that it wasn't doing you're
violating any of their Terms of Use
which I think are mmm yeah they're
complicated let's put it that way so
they're you can't do whatever you want
in other words so then they say okay you
either get approved or reject it if you
get rejected they may or may not be
specific about why you got rejected or
tell you if there's anything that you
can do about it so that approval process
can take some time it used to take a lot
of time it's much better now nowadays
it's it's more like you know a day I'm
told but you know usually but it you
know you can get rejected so that's not
cool that complicates matters especially
if you've on a deadline with a client
and there's an event coming up it can be
problematic then once it's in the App
Store you you know people it shows up so
people either your users potential users
are either searching around in the App
Store for the kind of thing that you do
maybe you have some sort of photo
editing application you know where you
can take a picture with the app and use
your finger to draw smuggles on it or
messages or funny-face or whatever and
so maybe people are searching in the App
Store for funny face pictures or meme
maker or something like that so you kind
of have an SEO situation like you would
with websites as if anybody who's built
websites or used websites knows you know
the this if you're searching for
something you usually start with a
search engine perhaps Google and you get
a huge list of results and then you
cruise through those and find the ones
that you think are gonna meet your need
so there's that discovery process in the
App Store and and that people have a
hard time with that the same way they
have a hard time getting
the front page or even the top of the
front page of a Google search result so
you can do things like buy ads inside
the App Store you can do things like you
know go around in and buy ads all over
the internet or do some marketing and
try and try and raise awareness of your
app so that people would search for it
by name in the App Store or perhaps go
to your website and click on Install Now
link which will take you to the App
Store so you know you're sort of that
you know people call it a walled garden
it's it's somebody else's store and they
maintain a high degree of control over
it it's highly curated and you were very
much at the whim of their you know taste
and on any given day so it's very it
feels like it people I don't know people
are probably too young to remember this
to remember the music business but I
used to be a musician I went to school
for music and in in the 90s
the music business in radio were a huge
gatekeeper you didn't matter really how
good you were nobody was gonna hear
music unless was on the radio that was
that was it that was the only way and
that's that's what the app store feels
like to me where you're saying like you
know if if Apple smiles on you and
features your app you're gonna have
millions of downloads but there's only
so much space to be featured and you're
in competition with Facebook and EA and
Google and you know so it's it's a it's
a very competitive marketplace so anyway
I'm sort of soapboxing about the idea of
being in an app store personally I'm not
a big fan of it in terms of for people
who are in their you know in their
apartment and they're thinking you know
I've got this day job and I'm thinking
about making an app that could make some
good side income for me the App Store
offers a lot of stuff done for you you
know you know you don't have to figure
out a payment system touch ID will just
work for you people can iOS users can
just buy your app it's very the barrier
to entry is very low for them to buy it
but your job and get
to be aware of it is pretty high for a
solo an indie developer it's pretty high
so that was a very long answer there
there are other ways to install apps
that we could talk about if you wanted
to keep talking about that I'd like to
find out if it's possible to take one of
these progressive web apps and package
it in such a way that it can be
distributed on the App Store and if
that's the case why would someone choose
to go that route mm-hmm the answer is
yes you can do that and the way you do
it is you you basically build a
special-purpose browser that has your
assets baked into it so it's almost like
a it's almost like a web browser that
can only go to one URL and you you
bundle that together and you submit that
as an app so the first and people call
that a hybrid app so it's kind of a mix
of a native app because it is installed
natively and it can access things like
the camera and your contact list and the
accelerometers and the you know
vibration motor but it was written you
know for a web developer this is
sometimes an attractive approach because
they can use their existing skills they
don't have to learn objective-c or Swift
or Android Java they can just use HTML
CSS and JavaScript mostly just
JavaScript and build an application that
would run in a browser at least in a
modern browser and then just sort of
bundle it together into an application
so the first hybrid app wrapper was
PhoneGap and that was extremely popular
it's so popular in fact that Adobe
bought the name and acquired the team
that built it and they spun out the the
core engine of it as an independent
open-source project under the Apache
foundation called Cordova so that's the
so Cordova and PhoneGap are almost
synonymous but not quite and another one
that people might be familiar with is
ionic which is a wrapper sort of a
convenience wrapper around
Cordova and so these are just these are
just sort of a leg up or it's like a
bunch of code that allows you to more
quickly get started wrapping your web
app as a hybrid native app let's see if
I understand when you wrap a web app as
a native app you are packaging it
together with a special purpose browser
and the Java Script is going to execute
in that browser and the rendering would
also be done in in the browser is that
right yeah it's browser is a loaded term
though it's it's actually a webview so
if you think of it as the part of the
browser in the big the big window part
of the browser but not the none of the
Chrome part of the browser so none of
the the URL bar is not there the you
know Safari tools at the bottom aren't
there so it's kind of like it's sort of
similar to if you go to say Twitter or
LinkedIn or Facebook or something and
you tap on a link and the screen slides
over and you're kind of on somebody's
website but you're still inside of
Facebook you know if you're familiar
with that experience it's just that
piece so it's just the webview piece or
there's different names for it
technically but it's it's a webview it's
a it's a it's a rectangle that
understands HTML CSS and JavaScript and
you can take that rectangle and bundle
it with some some sort of basic
resources that will allow it to work
offline and in in fact you can have some
native to JavaScript bridging that
allows JavaScript to go outside of the
normal browser sandbox and get access to
like your microphone I mean browsers can
kind of do that now anyway but
regardless the idea is that you you
write a web app and then you you stick
it in a wrapper which is a little bit
complicated but it's a heck of a lot
easier than learning how to develop a
native iOS app from scratch and you can
you can do that and you can make it work
that approach I was a lot more
interesting maybe five years ago
because especially for enterprise
customers who had of just hundreds or
maybe in in some cases more than a
thousand internal employee applications
that were web applications that were
typically accessed by their employees on
desktop computers and so imagine you're
in a situation where you're you're a CTO
of something like let's just say HP and
you've got a thousand literally a
thousand applications internal
applications like human resources and
professional development and 401k I mean
task tracking project management million
internal applications and and you've
been accessing them your employees have
been accessing the accessing them on the
desktop but now they want to access them
on their phones and you want them to do
this because it means that that's more
time they can be working so how do you
get how do you port a thousand what are
essentially web applications desktop web
applications over to mobile you're not
going to build them all natively that's
insane
so it would it's just not feasible you
know you couldn't do it so what you what
you could do was modify the existing web
applications to be a little smarter
about their screen size you know like oh
I detect that I'm on a you know a teeny
little screen that happens to have touch
capabilities so I'm gonna reconfigure my
sundar rearrange the furniture a little
bit here and you can allow people to
access those web apps from their phones
if some of those web apps needed device
access back it back could it back five
years ago the big one was the camera and
the contact list those are the two big
ones it's like okay and push
notifications as well those those three
things were big it's like you can't you
can't really do that with a web browser
in 2012 so okay what do we do we could
take we can modify our apps and the ones
that need camera access or push
notifications or contact access will
wrap those in PhoneGap and we can
distribute those there's there's a an
enterprise way to distribute apps to
employees that doesn't require the app
store so you could do
that and that made a ton of sense a few
years ago I would say to people who have
web skills now that if you want to find
the quickest path from your current
skill set and your tools that you like
to use and your current level of
expertise if you want to start making
mobile apps that are native then you
really should look at react react j/s
and react native it doesn't let you do
everything but it lets you do 80 or 90%
of anything you're gonna want to do and
it it makes just makes tons of sense to
a person who understands web development
so if you want to do front-end native
mobile nothing compares to react in my
opinion so that would be that would be
the first place I would send people
let's talk a little bit more about react
and react native what's the difference
between react j/s and react native okay
so this very little of importance so the
the mantra of the reactive team so like
the concept behind react was to change
the paradigm from write once run
everywhere which was kind of the the
feeling that was sort of the native web
debate so people who are into you know
building native iOS apps and people who
were into building mobile web pages and
mobile web apps it was like well I'm a
web developer and I'm superior to iOS
developers because the stuff I write
runs everywhere and the stuff that iOS
developers front-right only runs on iOS
so they're they're sort of at the mercy
of Apple in many ways this was perhaps
golden handcuffs maybe not a bad thing
but that was kind of the the sentiment
it was also the promise of Java way back
when write it once and run it everywhere
so the react team or say you know what
we're gonna think about this differently
we're gonna we're gonna say learn how to
take this approach and you can write
everywhere so you can write for
everything with using basically the same
so the difference between to get to your
specifics of your question the
difference between react je s and react
native there's some there's some
differences about setting up your
development environment but that's the
kind of thing you do once and it's over
with but the big difference is that when
you when you are well the big similarity
let's start there the big similarity is
that you're writing JavaScript so you
write JavaScript and if you're familiar
with writing JavaScript you're going to
be super comfortable writing react there
are a couple of concepts there are
little take a take a few minutes to not
to understand but to agree with the
premise of if you follow me so like like
with with react they want you to pass
data there's like no Global's and react
really what you really want to do is be
passing information from components up
and down the think of it as a Dom tree
so you at first I was kind of like well
what if you know that's kind of pain if
I got to pass something down like to a
distant ancestor but but after a while
you're like oh this is genius
so once the light bulb kind of goes on
for you with you know a couple of things
with react the core premises core
premise of react once the light bulb
goes on it's very easy to write it and
it's really easy to debug which is
fabulous so you're writing it it's just
like a JavaScript application and it
it's just like any other it's like
angular kind of it's like amber kind of
I mean they have tons of differences but
it's a similar kind of feel to it in
terms of complexity but what's cool
about react native is that you can't
just take the JavaScript that you wrote
for a react.js application and you can't
use it note for note as your react
native code but you can use almost all
of it so it's not the exact same
codebase but you can go through and for
example replace a div tag with a view
tag so like in a browser an HTML view
tag doesn't exist but on iOS a view is a
specific thing it's kind of like a div
in a sense it's like a rectangular
wrapper for a view well it's called a
view but you can might get my point see
it's kind of it's an oversimplification
but it's kind of like you can take your
react j/s code move it over into a react
native project and go through and
replace your divs with views and your
inputs with text area or something I
can't remember the exact tag names off
the top of my head but it's very very
similar so I I went from writing my
first react J s app to writing a react
native app in like one day it's really
easy and again it doesn't you can't do
everything that you perhaps want to do
in a native app with react but you can
do a lot of things so as a first step
it'd be it's it's a it's really a worth
any any web developer out there who's
interested in developing mobile apps
either for the browser or for an app
store should really look at react it's
the most exciting thing I've seen in the
last you know five or ten years in this
space great to summarize you said that
the creators of react are selling it as
a right Everywhere solution rather than
a write once run anywhere yes once ya
learn once right everywhere learn once
right everywhere this seems to mean that
although there are some differences in
the different platforms you perhaps
write some different code and adapt your
code to that platform but you're still
using the same paradigm in how you
developed a code and you're still using
the same tools what are some differences
that you'd need to address some
differences between the platforms yeah
some differences say between iOS and
Android that would require you to code
differently it would depend on your it
depends a lot on the kind of application
but you know just the big one is a
hardware back button so Android has a
prominent back concept that is
system-wide and goes across applications
and iOS adopted it I think two versions
ago where in the top left hand corner
you might see a little you know
back to Gmail button or something but
it's not it's not the kind of history
that you get on Android other things
that are different about Android that
you have to usually worry about are that
there's a much much wider range of
devices there's I mean it's some insane
number of Android devices like I don't
know I'm not even gonna guess it could
be ten thousand it could be a hundred
thousand and I wouldn't be surprised so
all the hardware is different and you
know the the layout of the the core
Android buttons could be in a different
place there's just a lot more
uncertainty in that platform so you
might have to code a little bit more
defensively there but it's it's really
thick its it's things like that you
might want to style I mean you're gonna
inherit your application is going to
inherit moving back up the react native
JavaScript that you write is at compile
time is converted to pure native code
for both platforms so the application
that's running at that on the user's
device is not a hybrid web app like a
PhoneGap thing it is pure native so you
you might if you are changing the look
of this if you're changing the standard
look of the normal iOS or Android
elements on a page you might want to do
that differently on iOS to Android so by
default you're gonna get the native look
and feel of like a ListView or a date
picker or something but if you want to
modify your date picker and do something
custom
you're probably gonna do that
modification you're gonna style it one
way on iOS and you're probably gonna
style it another way on Android so it
could be you know those sorts of things
they're just like little differences
where you don't want to throw some a
jarring sort of platform hostile design
and an Android user that you know that's
it's gonna make them wonder what is this
what am I supposed to do here how do I
use this date picker the date picker is
a good example because it's very
different on both platforms so if you're
gonna diverge from the standard date
picker you're still going to want to
make it platform specific
there's something interesting you said
there about design considerations and it
goes back to your statements about
progressive web apps and how as a
developer you have to think about the
different devices and different screen
sizes etc is there greater importance
and emphasis on design in mobile apps
versus web apps of your or desktop apps
is there a shift in the the composition
of teams to be more design heavy mm-hmm
I would say yes I'm tempted to say yes
but you can see even across the web you
can see that certain brands clearly
spend a lot of resources you know time
money bodies creating really beautiful
immersive web designs and some companies
don't so I think for companies who have
already been delivering that kind of
experience on the web the desktop web
you know I'm thinking Nike comes to mind
the Apple is another one that okay Wow
they've really spent a lot of time
creating a luxurious brand experience in
the web for them it probably won't
change things that much because their
internal makeup is already set up for
that it the skills might be a little
different in terms of implementing the
execution of the design but the design
itself I think it doesn't require
perhaps it might require a little bit of
learning but it doesn't I don't think we
wouldn't change the makeup of the teams
too much that's that's very that's a
soft answer though I mean that there
it depends big time but there are some
there's certain design consisted model
that are you know like on the web
desktop web you're using a pointer
device that does not obscure the screen
while you're doing it so you can put
your navigation at the very top of the
page because
is to move the mouse pointer up there
doesn't block the whole page but if you
move your finger up there your arm is
blocking the whole page so it makes a
lot more sense to put the controls at
the bottom which wasn't really a pattern
that we saw on the desktop web really I
can't even think of one example that had
the navigation at the bottom of the page
I mean obviously the footer but I'm
talking about the bottom of the viewport
and on mobile you really want to do that
not be not not only because using your
meat pointer to you know reach up to the
top of the screen is gonna block your
view of what you know of your
beautifully designed and crafted
experience but it's hard to reach you
know if you're holding the phone with
one hand which is the predominant usage
model your thumb is you're not even
using five fingers you're really just
using your thumb and it's got a sort of
fan like reach from you know if you're
holding it with your right hand you've
got this bottom right hand corner this
fan that it can reach so you want to put
all of your critical controls like
navigation in that area so that it's
easier for your users to reach without
adjusting their hand position or you
know there's things you can do on iOS
like like double touch the home button
and it brings the whole screen down but
you know they're so yes there are some
different design considerations but that
I think any designer who is user focused
and user centric is gonna find that very
it just works itself out it's not I
don't think that's a huge shift if your
organization hasn't devoted a lot of
resource and energy and time and money
to design in the past then yes I think
that you're gonna have an even harder
time building trust and engagement with
your mobile users because the bar is so
high on mobile for really gorgeous
high-resolution fast experiences how
important is design and human
interaction to the success of a web app
is it something that is damaging when
you don't meet the high bar
it really depends on who you're trying
so I would have a different answer for
b2c companies versus B to B or B to e so
if you've if you're you know what did I
say before HP and you've got a thousand
internal applications the you've got a
captive audience your employees aren't
gonna quit because you know you're I
don't know your human resources app
doesn't scroll buttery smooth you know
it's it's like look we just want to
check our 401 K can you give us way to
do that on our phones and if they you
know if they have to scroll down a you
know five times to find that information
on a long skinny web page you they're
not gonna quit you know would it be
nicer if you had something more
sophisticated yeah it would but you've
got a thousand apps to pour it over so
you know we'll get to when we get to it
so on that side I I mean would the
design be nicer if it was nicer yes that
would be nicer but is it something to
devote budget to probably not you know
probably more more important things to
budget for if on the flip side if you're
developing a game then you better darn
well make sure your graphics are
pristine and your your frame rates are
through the roof and your glitches are
non-existent you know so it's there's
just a spectrum of things that need to
be considered or something like I've
literally not bought productivity apps
because their icon was too ugly to look
at on my home screen I'm like you know
this is my actually my favorite app but
the icon is so ugly I cannot look at it
every single time I open my phone which
is probably 2 or 300 times a day I'm
just not not doing it so yeah I mean
they're they're different concerns on on
mobile from a design standpoint the bar
is way higher and I think pretty much
it's hard to think of an exception to a
consumer application that that you can
just have asked the design I can't even
think of one okay to summarize you
mentioned actually three categories of
of apps grouped by their audience
b2b so a business selling to another
business b2c a business selling to a
consumer and the third one I'm not sure
if you had an acronym for it but it was
a
so again ete so that's selling to an
internal customer what's the e and bt
employee business - employee okay I'd
like to go back and summarize a little
bit so far we've talked about three
approaches to mobile app development
progressive web apps native apps and
react native seems to be a third
category in that you're using web
technology to develop the the app but
it's targeted to the native platform
could is is it important as a developer
to understand how the technology works
what would be the impact if you didn't
understand the implication that you're
targeting the native platform really you
just want to you want to think about the
application that you're planning to
build and think through the roadmap of
features that you would want to add and
then just make sure that that react
supported it or xamarin is another one
I'm not super familiar with Samer and
it's more of a Windows thing and I'm
more of a Linux person in Mechelen linux
person but but that's another one there
were others there are others another one
accelerator was another one I think
they're still around and the the problem
with these the problem with some of them
the older ones that accepted the code
that you you are used to writing you
know so it could have been Ruby could
have in JavaScript will take your Ruby
or your JavaScript and will convert it
into objective-c and create an
application and the from a career
standpoint as a developer those always
turned me off because I was learning
their platform I was learning how to be
a titanium cellar 8 or titanium
developer and they didn't really want to
hitch my core my cart to that horse
because I was a web developer it was
like the felt like the freest kind of
developer where I could create something
and literally everyone globally who was
connected to the Internet could access
it immediately and I didn't I didn't
like the idea of betting on one betting
my skills and the time I was gonna spend
to learn things betting them on
somebody's proprietary this
some proprietary stack from a start-up
so that always kind of turned me off and
I never really that's why I stuck with
the sort of for native for me personally
the projects I would take on were either
gonna be mobile web projects or PhoneGap
projects where I was doing when back
when I used to do development I don't do
it anymore
but I would stick with that because I
wanted to be come better at HTML CSS and
JavaScript primarily JavaScript I didn't
want to get better at some companies
weird you know don't mean specific
language so that so that was a thing so
now with react
the thing about react that I love is
that I'm still writing JavaScript I'm
I'm writing and I'm writing it in a way
that even if I wrote react native miner
I don't know what's with a with a let's
just say minimal it depends on the app
but let's say minimal changes I could
use that same code and it would run in a
web browser but when it when I compile
it it is running it'll run as a purely
native app on iOS or Android so like
it's kind of like the best of all worlds
and on top of it Facebook it reactors
come out of Facebook and Facebook uses
it for applications native mobile
applications that are used by billions
of people so it's kind of hard to belie
and and they're sophisticated UI so it's
kind of hard to be like Oh beat you know
reacts and be limiting you know the
Facebook's not some little startup
they're making huge apps that are really
good-looking and cutting-edge at scale
so and not all of their apps are used
react but I'm trying remember I think
messenger is a react app their ad
manager is a react app I don't remember
for sure I could be wrong about those
but but they make really nice-looking
apps that are super fast very performant
well-designed that are cross-platform
and work at scale so that's good enough
for me
as a web developer
it sounds like you also have a feeling
of satisfaction when you're using react
can you describe that experience a
little bit why do you like to use it
sure I like the mentality so like the
thinking behind react is this is this is
super subtle so if people don't have a
lot of experience with this it might not
translate but back in the day when I
first started doing web development it
was around 2003 so what's that 14 years
ago 15 years ago and I started with PHP
and PHP I can I can hear people holding
their nose in the audience when I was a
PHP but I like PHP and it's a little bit
of a junk drawer but Minh
it was like the code that you would
inherit from from some PHP developer
back then was almost always just total
spaghetti code it was like it was like
an HTML page with inline CSS on the tags
with JavaScript sprinkled all over the
place with PHP tags springing all over
the place it was it was a it was it was
like a mess so when you inherited one of
these things even if it was your own if
you had to maintain it for a long period
of time it got really really frustrating
and people would do these weird things
to try and make it easier and everybody
had a different pattern and it was kind
of early days of web development with
with like a middleware so you know it's
not surprising that it it didn't come
out perfectly formed you know the
development practices and best best
practices and in standards they didn't
exist people every was just figuring it
out so what 10 15 years later well so
then in the middle phase everyone was
like separation of concerns that will
solve the spaghetti code problem and we
started writing unobtrusive javascript
and we started taking all of our CSS and
moving it outside of the HTML so it
wasn't on individual tags it was it was
sort of you had your HTML which
described your content you're marked up
marked up content and that was your
document and then you had a one or more
CSS files that were included that
that selected items in that page and
would modify them differently with
different CSS so this was the heyday of
something called CSS Zen garden where
different developers could it could
provide different CSS and it was kind of
like it was kind of like a competition
to see how different you could make the
exact same HTML page look with your
different kind of CSS back and at the
time it was pretty hard because CSS
wasn't very advanced so that was kind of
like that was pretty eye-opening like
wow I can I can completely separate the
styling of a webpage from the content
and the markup of the webpage that's
cool and then we sort of did the same
thing with JavaScript and it was called
unobtrusive javascript where you you
could look through the HTML page and you
didn't see any JavaScript in there
javascript was all included from one or
more external files that would just like
CSS it would you could say hey any
elements any submit buttons in this for
any forms on submit we're gonna run this
handle or function and do some Ajax and
and that was sort of the second big wave
of web development getting more
sophisticated so first we separated up
the CSS and then we separated out the
JavaScript and maybe things happen at
the same time but that's how I remember
it and it's what we ended up with was
and I think right before react came out
I was feeling this pretty hard if you
get a really complicated application a
web application that has lots of markup
lots of CSS and lots of JavaScript it
becomes really brittle because it's all
separated but it physically in the files
so we've separated the concerns based on
the technology HTML in these files CSS
and these files javascript in these
files but they were tightly coupled it
depended on how flexible you're worth
your selectors but the what was
happening was tightly coupled so if you
had a sophisticated let's go back to the
date picker you had a sophisticated
calendar widget or a date picker that
was for a vacation rental that had
blackout dates and you couldn't you know
in half days when you could register
really complicated calendar picker you
would have HTML in one place and you'd
have CSS a lot of HTML in one place a
lot of CSS in another place in a lot of
JavaScript somewhere else so it was
really hard to know when you change
something in your CSS which is global if
it was going to affect your calendar
widget you know I want to change the way
the header looks on this web page whoops
I broke the calendar widget what those
things aren't even related but the way
that CSS works and in to a certain
extent JavaScript as well
it's very global on the page so the
separation of concerns was this sort of
technology-based thing which was better
than the old PHP spaghetti code where
everything was just dumped into the bowl
but it still had this problem where you
would regularly find yourself you know
creating regression bugs so like you you
would change something over here it was
like this whack-a-mole thing changed
something in the CSS for the header and
boom your calendar widget breaks so huh
what do we do about that along comes
react and react when I first saw it I
had I had a negative reaction to it
because the first example I saw mixed
together the it's not exactly CSS but it
looks like CSS and the JavaScript and
the markup all in one blob and I was
like this is spaghetti code all over
again what a bad idea and I said you
know and I just I was like it rejected
it out of hand I said this is this is
not smart so I came back to it a little
while later because I can't remember why
someone convinced me to give it a second
look and again I had the same reaction
but then I actually just tried it and
the lightbulb went on and I was like
okay what we're doing here is we have a
different kind of separation of concerns
it's a different way to solve the
spaghetti code problem and it's a way
that for complicate complicated web
applications is really really smart
where all of your everything that you
need to know about your calendar widget
is encapsulated in this one little place
so even if even a very complicated
calendar widget it's gonna be like
vallabha code maybe it's a page-long
which bill oh wow that's so much code
for the calendar widget but you can with
impunity change other things about the
overall application and never worry for
a second that those changes are gonna
touch the calendar widget this is
incredibly important I mean this is
important enough if you're just
developing by yourself but if you have
teams this is critical because if you've
got a team that's working on the
scheduling module which has the calendar
widget and you've got another marketing
team developers working inside the
marketing team to change the offers on
the pricing page the pricing team can
break your calendar widget so this is
like you know if you don't use a react
cell but if you do use a react style
everything is compartmentalized and and
it's good for you even if you're a solo
person but it's also very good for for
the team if you you know if you're in a
team environment it's amazing but you
know it's for something really simple
it's overkill but things get you know
there's not a lot of mobile app
experiences I can think of they're just
simple it's there's not that many of
them so if you're doing anything that's
remotely complicated it's probably worth
the it's not over engineering for
something that's it's starting to get a
little bit complicated for things that
are really really basic like I don't
know an app that just does want like I
can't even I even a to-do app is
complicated enough so I it's it's it
feels like spaghetti good at first but
when you recognize that what happens is
they've just separated the concerns
differently they've separated them in a
functional way or a component way
instead of in a technology way all of a
sudden it's like wow this is super cool
by keeping these units of functionality
separate and keeping the information
about the style and the logic and these
units is that what provides the
separation of concerns yes so you can
you can it makes it easier to reason
about what's going to happen when you
make a change so you're like oh I can
see everything I need to see it's almost
like it's almost like if you had if you
had a web application
that was designed and what I would call
the standard way which is HTML all of
your HTML for a page in one place all
the CSS probably for the entire site in
another place and all of your JavaScript
probably for the entire site in another
place it's almost like you said you
could say to your development
environment okay I need to make a change
to this calendar widget show me all the
CSS JavaScript a markup together somehow
and your development environment go okay
let me go off and get that stuff did you
do pull it together
here you go and you can sort of do this
with the browser
you know developer tools in chrome you
can kind of see like okay I can kind of
see that but it's not great and more
importantly you would want your
development environment to be able to
tell you if I change this thing on the
sales page what else is gonna change and
with and there's just no good way to get
that answer you know possibly you could
say well like 100% test coverage would
give you that answer but that's really
hard too so with react you can look you
can see everything probably in a page
maybe two pages at the most
okay I'm gonna look I want to change
this what else is it going to affect
it's not gonna affect anything outside
this page so you know you can make
changes with impunity knowing that
you're not breaking something somewhere
else or some other teams code in episode
293 of software engineer radio we had
yakov fine as a guest and he talked
about angular as a component based
architecture is the react pattern or
architecture something you described as
component based you mentioned the word
component is there a similarity there
I'm not super familiar with an angular I
would anger at the very beginning and
now that they just broke backwards
compatibility and I think I think
angular 2 was the break it's so I
haven't really followed it so I can't
really answer that question but my
understanding is that well I I'm not
even going my understanding is based on
early versions of one so I really can't
answer that question
I don't see angular as a mobile solution
at all though angular for me angular is
a desktop browser framework another
thing that Jakov mentioned is that he
viewed angular as a framework and react
as a library is that does that fit with
your understanding or do you do you
think of things in those terms and the
reason he said that is that he viewed
angular as being more opinionated
whereas he felt that for react
developers had to be well he used the
word smarter and perhaps no more is that
is that the is that the case or what's
your view I agree with that I would
agree with that and I think amber is
even more opinionated than angular and
those are the three that usually get
discussed and in fact that's that was
one of the reasons why I sort of
dismissed a react out of hand is because
I was like and this is another angular
this is another amber you know it's it's
too opinionated for me I like more
flexibility and it I think react does
offer more you you don't get a lot of
opinionation opinionations it's not
pushy react is not pushy there are a
couple of core concepts that there's
there's that you don't want to violate
you might not agree with them at first
until you understand why they're great
and then once you understand you know
like unidirectional data flow it's it's
amazing it's so great in terms of like
if you've got experience building not
even complicated but but somewhat
complicated web applications or
applications of any kind and you know
stuff that involves network network
requests to servers that are updating
information in a database it doesn't
take long for you to be like man I've
got race conditions everywhere I and I'm
getting these weird bugs from them I
don't know how to handle it I've got
things happening in the interface you
know the user is interacting with this
thing I need to update things all over
the place based on you know the oh they
read this email so I have to update
numbers in five places you know it's it
gets very complicated it's like how do I
send that information the information
across the Dom do I send it to the
server and bring it back react is like
there's just like nope there's one way
to do it
you you update the data everything else
and then it it goes from there the data
is the data store is like the top of the
mountain and everything flows down to
the interface from there the interface
it does not go the other way it's like
so other than then that there's not you
know and like I said passing parameters
from from you know parent to child is
pretty strictly adhere to like not doing
that you might as well not be using to
react like that's so I would agree with
that I would call anger and Ember
frameworks that allow you to create
something pretty amazing
pretty fast and I think that react
creates amazing things but it's in a
different way it's like wow I just wrote
this code base that I can you know dupe
and find replace practically and create
a native applications on iOS and Android
and and I didn't have to learn anything
but a couple of patterns and just use
JavaScript so it's amazing in a
different way it doesn't like there's no
user interface widgets didn't react not
that there's none you could probably
include them from somewhere someone
probably has created them but it doesn't
care about that it's more about the the
the studs in the walls then the picture
hanging on the wall or the door you know
it's like it's like an internal thing
that you use so you do stuff under the
hood you know or more like a better
analogy would be like a car it's it's
the engine that you use it's not it
doesn't care about the seats of the
dashboard or how you want it want the
fit and finish to be in the cabin so
Jonathan we're running out of time and
we've covered a lot of information it
seems that many of these topics could be
shows in their own right you've given us
a really good overview of the native
ecosystem and it sounds like you're
really excited about react native is
there anything that I haven't asked you
about mobile development or about react
native that you think we should cover
mmm I wouldn't I mean we talked about
react native a lot it's not it's not the
thing I'm most excited about in mobile
honestly but the things that I'm most
excited about in mobile
probably a little bit more of a stretch
to call applications so you know I'm
super interested in machine learning and
AI because of the capabilities that it
can add you know the virtual assistant
concept can add to a mobile phone that
you have with you always and is always
on and virtually always connected I'm
super interested in chat BOTS which I
think are I just think they're gonna be
it's not like I think mobile apps are
gonna go away but most people have I
think 10 to 12 applications on their
phone that they use on a regular basis
in the top 10 nine of them are owned by
Facebook and Google and the other one is
snapchat so the concept of creating a
mobile app that is going to be a
long-term you know like squeezing into
that list is I just feel like that that
that race is over in Facebook and Google
want it so I think it's you know it
depends on your use key like the things
that get me excited are a little bit
more like yeah it's really cool that
with react you can build these these
native apps people still want native
apps you can build them with your web
skills I love that you can repurpose it
for the web I love that I don't feel
like that's where things are happening
though like is not I shouldn't say
happening that is where things are
happening I don't feel like that's the
future for me the future is more
conversational computing interfaces
whether text-based voice based or both
and in a continued proliferation of
peripherals that are enabled by mobile
things like Amazon it Alexa in Google
home and you know those sorts of things
that wearables and medical devices and
and all of those things I think are in
play for mobile developments so the
reason I say that is because dear
listener I don't want you to feel like
you know you need to make this app to
put in the App Store to be playing in
the mobile space if you're more of a
back-end person build a chatbot go to
what is it a pIJ I you can build a
chatbot right now for slack that'll
install in slack and Facebook Messenger
and
so on and so forth there's like a dozens
of integration as possible there's so
many cool things to talk about if you're
building mobile apps react is definitely
something to look at but if you want to
do other things in mobile there's a
million other things to talk about so
thanks for pointing out these other
possibilities and I don't want to
restrict my idea of mobile apps just to
native apps and it's been really helpful
to have you on the show
and give that broad perspective Jonathan
where can listeners find out more about
you and follow what you're doing best
place would be especially for this
audience would be the other podcasts I
do I do three other podcasts you
mentioned two of them one is the
freelancers show which is for folks who
are perhaps going out on their own
to do software development another one
is ditching hourly which is for a you
know similar audience independent
software developers who recognize that
hourly billing is a mistake and
something they don't enjoy and then a
more futuristic nology podcast that I
don't think we mentioned earlier called
terrifying robot dog that I do with my
co-host kelly shaver and we talked about
how technology is affecting the way we
interact with the world so depending on
where you're at dear listener one or the
other or the other of those might be of
interest we'll have links to those shows
in our show notes
Jonathan stark it's been a pleasure
speaking with you for software
engineering radio this has been Nate
black thanks for listening
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by
out your police software magazine for
more about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening